Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是斯科特-曼利
In a few weeks a science fiction movie is getting released
再过几周 一部科幻电影就要上映了
which I can claim to have had a small part in helping create.
我可以说我在帮助创作方面有一点贡献
The movie is Stowaway.
这部电影就是《偷渡》
It's written by Joe Penna also known as the mystery guitar man
它的作者是乔-潘纳 也被称为神秘的吉他手
and Ryan Morrison who I don't know his alias.
和Ryan Morrison 我不知道他的化名
But when they first got in touch in 2015 they had most of the story in nearly the final form
但当他们在2015年第一次接触时 他们的大部分故事几乎是最终形式的
but they've been taking on or talking to advisers about space stuff,
但他们一直在接受或与顾问讨论有关太空的事情
you know, astronauts, engineers at JPL, experts in spacecraft design
你知道 宇航员 JPL的工程师 航天器设计专家
and somehow they found me.
不知何故 他们找到了我
I'm not a rocket scientist.
我不是一个火箭科学家
I just play one on the internet.
我只是在互联网上扮演一个
but I do frequently point out mistakes in science fiction movies
但我确实经常指出科幻电影中的错误
and yeah on my twitters I will suggest how they could have been fixed
是的 在我的推特上 我将建议如何修复这些错误
if only the producers had gone and asked me.
如果制片人去问我的话
So now they asked me.
所以现在他们问我
Yes a C-list youtube celebrity with a funny accent.
是的 一个有搞笑口音的C级YouTube名人
But yeah I totally jumped at the chance.
但是 是的 我完全抓住了这个机会
I mean I like actually Joe's work on youtube
我的意思是 我其实很喜欢乔在Youtube上的作品
so I was like great I'll totally work with you.
所以我觉得很好 我完全可以和你一起工作
So I read the script.
所以我读了剧本
We had a few phone calls.
我们打了几个电话
I sent a lot of emails over the last few years
在过去的几年里 我发了很多电子邮件
and in the end I couldn't spend any time
但最后我没能花任何时间
to get the spare the time to get face to face with the crew and help them design things
腾出时间与工作人员面对面 帮助他们设计东西
but now I've seen the final product
但现在我已经看到了最终的产品
I'm actually really happy with what I've seen.
我实际上对我所看到的非常满意
And there's a few things that I suggested actually made it onto the screen which is very cool
有几件我建议的事情居然被搬上了银幕 这非常酷
but before we dissect the whole movie we're going to have to wait for it to be released.
但在我们剖析整部电影之前 我们将不得不等待它的发布
But we do have a trailer and the trailer does have a few things that I want to talk about.
但我们确实有一个预告片 预告片中确实有一些我想谈的东西
Now obviously there's going to be some spoilers in here
现在很明显 这里会有一些破坏性的内容
but yeah we've only got a two minute trailer
但我们只有一个两分钟的预告片
so there's a lot more of the movie which I'm not going to cover until after it's released
所以电影还有很多内容 我不打算在它发布后再介绍
because I don't want to spoil anything for you right.
因为我不想破坏你的东西 对吗？
So anyway yeah if you have watched the trailer there's a few things that are very obvious.
所以 无论如何 如果你看了预告片 有几件事是非常明显的
First up it's a movie set in space with a very small cast.
首先 这是一部以太空为背景的电影 演员阵容非常小
It's got three astronauts and the titular stowaway on a spacecraft going to Mars
它有三个宇航员和名义上的偷渡者在一艘前往火星的宇宙飞船上
and of course there's not enough oxygen to keep the extra passenger alive
当然 没有足够的氧气来维持额外乘客的生命
which means the crew is going to be faced with some really tough decisions
这意味着船员们将面临一些非常艰难的决定
that will really stretch their acting skills.
这意味着船员们将面临一些非常艰难的决定 这将使他们的表演技巧得到真正的发挥
Now anybody that knows science fiction will recognize the parallels with the classic story the cold equations.
现在 任何了解科幻小说的人都会认识到与经典故事《冷酷方程式》的相似之处
Originally published in the 1950s it's a classic story
它最初发表于20世纪50年代 是一个经典故事
but hard decisions being made based on cold hard math.
但在冷酷的数学基础上做出艰难的决定
There's no other way out of the situation
在这种情况下 没有其他办法
so yes the story very much falls into this mode
因此 是的 这个故事在很大程度上属于这种模式
although it's worth noting that the cold equations itself
尽管值得注意的是 冷酷的方程式本身
isn't actually the first example of this particular storyline.
实际上并不是这种特殊故事情节的第一个例子
There's examples that date back to the 19th century.
有一些例子可以追溯到19世纪
But let me address a couple of responses I've seen in comments to the trailer
但让我谈谈我在对预告片的评论中看到的几个反应
talking about the science in the science fiction.
谈论科幻小说中的科学
Firstly lots of people are looking at the trailer
首先 很多人在看预告片的时候
and seeing the characters are walking around on the spaceship as if there's regular gravity
看到人物在飞船上走来走去 仿佛有正常的重力
and some of you have immediately dismissed the movie as fantasy
而你们中的一些人立即将这部电影斥为幻想
because artificial gravity isn't a realistic technology
因为人工重力并不是一项现实的技术
but if you look carefully at the trailer there is an explanation already in there.
但如果你仔细看一下预告片 里面已经有了解释
There's a couple of shots showing the spacecraft.
有几个镜头显示了航天器
And what you actually see are three modules joined together by very long cables
而你实际上看到的是三个模块被很长的电缆连接在一起
and the whole thing is rotating to simulate gravity
整个东西都在旋转以模拟重力
and this idea of joining spacecraft like this and spinning them is a real concept.
像这样连接航天器并使其旋转的想法是一个真实的概念
In fact there was a test of tethers in orbit with a Gemini 11 and the Agena Target Vehicle.
事实上 曾有一次用双子座11号和Agena目标飞行器在轨道上进行系绳测试
They docked them together then they undocked and they were tethered.
他们把它们对接在一起 然后解开 它们被拴住了
Now originally what they wanted to show
现在 他们最初想展示的是
was that they could keep the Gemini passively stable
是他们可以保持双子座的被动稳定
by having the Agena down near the earth and the Gemini up here
通过让阿吉娜号在地球附近降落 让双子座在这里上升
but orbital mechanics wouldn't cooperate with this idea and the tether kept on going slack.
但轨道力学不会与这个想法合作 系绳一直在松弛
So instead they showed that they could keep the tether taught by spinning the spacecraft
因此 他们表明 他们可以通过旋转航天器来保持系绳的稳定
and generating a tiny amount of artificial gravity
并产生微量的人工重力
that it was like less than one percent of a G
这就像不到百分之一的G
but it was enough to show the concept.
但它足以显示这个概念
So in stowaway this thing is scaled up to a multi-module space habitat
因此 在偷渡中 这个东西被放大为一个多模块的空间栖息地
with a booster as a counterweight hundreds of meters away
有一个作为配重的助推器在数百米之外
and the whole thing is rotating maybe a few times per minute.
而且整个东西每分钟可能旋转几次
It is a very cool design.
这是一个非常酷的设计
And when I first saw the script, the basic design was in there
而当我第一次看到这个剧本时 基本的设计就在里面了
I didn't have anything to do with that.
我没有任何关系
But as I understand it
但据我所知
the new writers they arrived at this design long after starting on the basic story
新的编剧在开始创作基本故事后很久才想到这个设计
because they realized that shooting a movie set in zero G would make a much more expensive production
因为他们意识到 在零重力环境下拍摄电影会使制作成本大大增加
so they wanted to try to keep the cost down
所以他们想尽量减少成本
so the first of all they wanted okay gravity
所以他们首先想要的是好的重力
let's have a ring-shaped spacecraft to generate artificial gravity
让我们有一个环形的航天器来产生人工重力
but there's two problems with this.
但这有两个问题
One is that if you make the spacecraft small enough
一个是 如果你把航天器做得足够小
then the curvature is quite extreme which means that you then have to build a set that has big curves on it
那么曲率就会很极端 这意味着你必须建造一个有大曲线的装置
and then you have to deal with the fact that people might need to walk around it.
然后 你必须处理人们可能需要在它周围行走的事实
Now for the movie 2001 they actually built a 27 ton centrifuge set for the main bridge of the discovery
现在 在电影《2001》中 他们实际上为发现的主桥建造了一个27吨的离心机组
which this whole thing could be rotated as they were shooting
当他们拍摄时 这整个东西可以旋转
and there's a couple of scenes in the movie where there's one actor walking around the bottom as it rotates
在电影中 有几场戏是这样的：一个演员在底部旋转时走动
and there's another actor basically strapped into their seat so they can go upside down.
而另一个演员基本上被绑在他们的座位上 所以他们可以倒立
Obviously this is some amazing film making.
显然 这是一些惊人的电影制作
I mean it's Stanley Kubrick, a director who would go to great lengths to shoot things the way he wanted.
我的意思是 这是斯坦利-库布里克 一个会不遗余力地按照他想要的方式来拍摄的导演
There's a joke that if Stanley Kubrick had been asked to fake the moon landings
有一个笑话说 如果斯坦利-库布里克被要求伪造登陆月球
he would have insisted on shooting it on the moon.
他一定会坚持在月球上拍摄
But anyway yeah this costs a lot of money
但无论如何 这要花很多钱
but also from a scientific point of view the small ring also would need to rotate faster
但从科学的角度来看 小环也需要更快旋转
and that actually causes problems with the crew.
而这实际上会给工作人员带来问题
They get dizzy because if they stand up and sit down
他们会感到头晕 因为如果他们站起来和坐下来
the rotation actually changes between their heads and their feet
旋转实际上在他们的头和他们的脚之间发生变化
and that makes them gives them nausea.
而这让他们感到恶心
So if you then said well why don't we scale up the radius of the habitat
因此 如果你说 我们为什么不扩大栖息地的半径呢？
so you don't need to have curved sets and things like that
这样你就不需要有弯曲的套装和类似的东西了
and the rotation is slower and the human body is fine.
而且旋转的速度更慢 人体就会很好
That solves those problems but then you have the problem of explaining
这就解决了这些问题 但是你又有一个问题 那就是如何解释
why the crew is so small on this massive ring spacecraft
为什么在这个巨大的环形飞船上 船员人数如此之少？
because having a small crew means a small number of cast members
因为有一个小的船员意味着有少量的演员
but also from a storytelling perspective
但从讲故事的角度来看
it's much more plausible that if your crew is supposed to be three and you have one extra
如果你的船员应该是三个人 而你却多了一个人 这就更有说服力了
that's a much bigger deal than if your crew is say 10.
这比你的船员是10人要大得多
I think an early version of the script actually had four crew members and a stowaway
我认为剧本的早期版本实际上有四个船员和一个偷渡者
and this was paired back to make the scenario more plausible.
而这是为了使剧情更加合理而配上的
So that's more or less how the riders came to this idea
所以 这或多或少是骑手们的想法
which had a small module and a very long cable.
它有一个小模块和一条很长的电缆
They wanted to make a space movie and they wanted to keep the costs low
他们想拍一部太空电影 他们想保持低的成本
and moreover once this design was settled on it actually drove other aspects of the storytelling
此外 一旦这个设计被确定下来 它实际上推动了故事的其他方面的发展
including a really cool set piece which we glimpse in the trailer
包括我们在预告片中瞥见的一个非常酷的场景
where the crew are in spacesuits climbing the cables between the modules.
我们在预告片中看到了一个非常酷的场景 工作人员穿着宇航服在模块之间的电缆上攀爬
Anyway I guess one contribution I can say that I did make was that
总之 我想我可以说的一个贡献是 我确实做出了贡献
I suggested in the design that they have a utility module in the middle
我在设计中建议 他们在中间有一个实用模块
because that's the place where the rotational forces are the lowest
因为那是旋转力最小的地方
so that's the best place to put your solar panels for your power generation.
所以那是放置太阳能板发电的最佳位置
Anyway during my work on this I generated some of the first renderings of the design as a reference.
总之 在我工作期间 我生成了一些设计的最初效果图作为参考
I used the power of Kerbal Space Program.
我使用了Kerbal Space Program的力量
I literally threw a design together in a few minutes and sent it to Joe
我在几分钟内就完成了设计 并把它发给了乔
and he was sort of blown away.
他被吓了一跳
And later I made a video showing the whole thing
后来我做了一个视频 展示了整个设计
as a sort of corporate promo video to explain the operation of this.
作为一种企业宣传片来解释它的运作
And that sort of brings me to another point
这让我想到另一个问题
which at least one journalist pointed out why don't they just turn around right.
至少有一位记者指出 他们为什么不直接转身呢？
Well we actually knew this would be asked
其实我们知道会有这样的问题
and I wrote a really long email explaining the math so that they would know.
我写了一封很长的电子邮件 解释了计算方法 以便他们知道
We hear that they've just left Earth about 12 hours ago
我们听说他们在12小时前刚刚离开地球
and with the crew in danger and the stowaway facing a two-year mission or death
船员处于危险之中 偷渡者面临两年的任务或死亡
surely it's better to just turn around and go home.
肯定会有更好的办法 就是转身回家
And the simple answer to this is that they don't have the fuel to slow down and turn around.
而这个问题的简单答案是 他们没有燃料来减速和转弯
Now if you do the basic orbital mechanics for holmen transfer orbit from the earth to Mars
现在 如果你做一个从地球到火星的霍门转移轨道的基本轨道力学研究
then after you reach escape velocity and escape the earth sphere of influence
那么在你达到逃逸速度并逃离地球的影响范围之后
you're moving at about four kilometers per second.
你的运动速度大约为每秒4公里
And that's what you'd need to turn around and go home
这就是你转身回家所需的速度
but to get into orbit and once you reach Mars that only takes two kilometers per second
但是进入轨道 一旦你到达火星 只需要每秒两公里的速度
so a mission plan that was expecting to refuel at Mars
所以一个期望在火星上加油的任务计划
might only have two kilometers per second repellent on board.
可能船上只有每秒两公里的驱赶剂
Therefore unable to turn around.
因此无法转身
As it happens the story ended up evolving to use a different type of transfer trajectory.
碰巧的是 故事最后演变为使用不同类型的转移轨道
The spacecraft is what's called a cycler
该航天器是所谓的循环器
and that's a spacecraft which is on an orbit around the sun that regularly brings it past the earth and Mars.
那是一个在围绕太阳的轨道上的航天器 定期将它带过地球和火星
The idea is that you have a large deep space accommodations in this big orbit and that thing never stops.
这个想法是 你在这个大的轨道上有一个大型的深空住宿 而且这个东西永远不会停止
The crew who wants to travel from Earth to Mars they leave Earth on a very small spaceship
想从地球到火星旅行的船员 他们乘坐一个非常小的飞船离开地球
accelerate up to catch this dock with it and they live in comfort for a few months.
加速赶上这个码头 他们在舒适的环境中生活几个月
And then when they get close to Mars they get back in their spaceship and leave and land on Mars
然后当他们接近火星时 他们回到他们的宇宙飞船上 离开并降落在火星上
and the whole thing is it means you only need to boost this space a tail up to speed once.
而整个事情是 这意味着你只需要将这个空间的尾巴提升到速度一次
Buzz Alderin is generally credited with the Earth-Mars cycler
巴兹-阿尔德林通常被认为是地球-火星循环器的功臣
we actually sometimes call them Alderin cyclers.
实际上 我们有时称它们为阿尔德林循环器
He did the math and the orbital mechanics for this.
他为这个做了数学和轨道力学的研究
But he basically showed that
但他基本上表明
they didn't need huge amount of maneuvers to keep them in synchronization with the Earth-Mars windows.
他们不需要大量的机动性来保持他们与地球-火星窗口的同步
But the cycler concept in general is believed to originate in the 1960s with a guy called Walter Hollister
但一般来说 循环器的概念被认为起源于20世纪60年代 一个叫沃尔特-霍利斯特的家伙
who looked at the cycler between Earth and Venus.
他研究了地球和金星之间的循环器
Now the downside to the cycler orbit is that it's more eccentric
现在 环形轨道的缺点是 它的偏心程度更高
and the encounter speeds at Earth and Mars are higher.
而且地球和火星的相遇速度更高
But since you're only moving a very small spacecraft up to speed and slowing down
但是 由于你只是把一个非常小的航天器移到速度上 然后放慢速度
it actually turns out to be a net win in terms of the amount of mass you're moving around.
就你所移动的质量而言 它实际上是一个净赢
And of course this feeds into the reasons for
当然 这也涉及到以下原因
why the crew can't just turn their ship around and avoid making those literal life or death decisions.
为什么船员们不能把他们的飞船转过来 避免做出那些字面上的生死决定
Now because the Earth-Mars transfer windows don't line up with the Mars-Earth windows
现在 由于地球-火星的转移窗口与火星-地球的窗口不一致
you actually need to have two cyclers one that's aligned for the outbound trip to Mars
你实际上需要有两个循环器 一个是对准火星的出站行程
and another that's set up for the inbound trip back to Earth.
而另一个则是为返回地球的行程而设置的
But two is actually just a lower limit for a fleet of cyclers.
但两个实际上只是一个循环器舰队的下限
You might need even more if you need them.
如果你需要 你可能需要更多
Like one of the important features of a cycler orbit is that
就像循环器轨道的一个重要特点是
they use gravity assists during close encounters with the earth
它们在与地球近距离接触时使用重力助推器
to twist the orbit around and make sure that the bigger orbit aligns with the windows.
来扭转轨道 确保更大的轨道与窗口对齐
And it needs to correct by a certain amount during this Earth encounter
而在这个与地球的相遇过程中 它需要修正一定的量
and the closer to Earth you get, the more the correction is.
而且离地球越近 修正量就越大
But sometimes the amount of correction you need is so big
但有时你需要的修正量是如此之大
that you you would actually end up inside the earth.
以至于你实际上会在地球内部结束
And that's not good. Yeah it's really not good.
这就不妙了 是的 这真的不是好事
So in that case the cycler would have to expend propellant in deep space
所以在这种情况下 循环器将不得不在深空消耗推进剂
to make sure that it can change its orbit enough to keep the orbit on target.
以确保它能改变它的轨道 以保持轨道的目标
Now ideally you could get this down to zero
现在 在理想的情况下 你可以把它降低到零
and there are designs which get your trajectory or changes down to zero.
而且有一些设计可以使你的轨道或变化降至零
But some of them for example have problems
但其中一些设计有问题 例如
where they don't get to make it to every single Earth-Mars window
他们无法到达每一个地球-火星窗口
and so you then would have to have extra cycler sitting out there
因此 你将不得不有额外的循环器坐在那里
to make sure you don't miss any transfer windows.
以确保你不会错过任何转移窗口
There are other designs though which use multiple Earth encounters
还有其他一些设计 它们使用多次与地球相遇的方式
so they go from Earth to Mars and then they come back
所以他们从地球到火星 然后他们回来
and have an Earth encounter and then another Earth encounter
然后有一次与地球的相遇 然后又一次与地球的相遇
and because they've got two they can use that to shape the orbit more efficiently
因为他们有两个 他们可以利用这一点来更有效地塑造轨道
and in theory get away with a ballistic orbit.
并在理论上摆脱弹道轨道
But regardless by the time we see this space station in the movie
但无论如何 当我们在电影中看到这个空间站时
it's been in service probably for a couple of decades.
它已经服役了几十年了
It's a lived-in vehicle.
它是一个生活中的交通工具
It might even have started out as a zero-G habitat.
它甚至可能一开始就是一个零重力的栖息地
And evolved over successive crews delivering new parts with each trip.
并且在每次旅行时 通过连续的工作人员提供新的部件而不断发展
All these crews will have left their mark.
所有这些工作人员都会留下他们的痕迹
And if you look at the set design in the background
如果你看一下背景中的场景设计
you can actually catch some clues as to these these cues I gave to them.
你实际上可以抓住一些线索 了解我给他们的这些线索
To be clear the spacecraft being a cycler has like zero influence on the story.
要清楚的是 飞船是一个循环器 对故事的影响是零
It's barely referenced in the dialogue.
它在对话中几乎没有被提及
I think there's like one mention of it.
我想只有一次提到它
It doesn't change any of that.
它并没有改变任何东西
But I just think it's really cool to see this hard science fiction idea outside of a hard sci-fI novel
但我只是认为 在一部硬科幻小说之外看到这种硬科幻的想法真的很酷
and a movie with Anna Kendrick in it that people might actually see and might learn something
和一部有安娜-肯德里克参演的电影 人们可能真的会看到 并可能学到一些东西
so look I think I'm leaving it there
所以 我想我要把它留在那里
because we can't talk about much more without getting outside the trailer.
因为如果不在预告片之外 我们就无法谈论更多
I'm excited for it.
我对它感到兴奋
It's not perfect in every way in terms of the science.
就科学而言 它在各方面并不完美
For sure there's a lot of things a lot of compromises that did have to be made.
可以肯定的是 有很多东西 有很多妥协 确实必须做出
But it's been a fantastic experience and I really can't wait to tell you more about it later.
但这是一个奇妙的经历 我真的迫不及待地想在以后告诉你更多关于它的事情
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是斯科特-曼利 飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]